If you're planning a family or
are pregnant, this video
is essential. As we all know,
pregnancy is a very emotional and
beautiful journey, and being a new mother is something I can totally
relate to. However, if
you haven't planned financially during pregnancy,
it can be very
stressful. Therefore, in this video,
we'll discuss maternity health
insurance, its features, and
why it's important for you to get it.
In this video, we'll discuss the
essential trimester-wise tests for pregnancy and their coverage;
IVF treatments and
how they're insured; delivery and
newborn care expenses; and how much
you might have to bear if you don't have a health insurance plan.
First, let's
understand the features and conditions of maternity health insurance. Let's
first discuss the waiting period.
Maternity plans typically have waiting periods of
3 months to 3 years, but
with today's new-age plans, you can
opt for maternity health insurance even up to the second trimester.
Now, let's discuss it.  Eligibility
Criteria: The
policyholder should be between 18 and 45 years of age when purchasing maternity health insurance. It's
also important to note
that many policies include health coverage. For
delivery expenses,
whether it's a normal delivery
or a C-section,
maternity health insurance covers both. For
newborn coverage, the
baby receives automatic coverage for 90 days after delivery. After that,
you'll need to inform your health insurance provider
about your gestational tests and scans. Regular
tests, ultrasounds, and genetic tests are all covered under the policy.
These
policies don't include them. Let's talk about
trimester-wise pregnancy tests
and their coverage. These include blood tests,
ultrasounds, and urine tests.
Doctor consultations are
also covered, but
supplements and prenatal vitamins aren't. The
second trimester test
covers glucose tolerance tests and triple marker tests.
Your routine diagnostic
tests and advanced ultrasounds are also
covered under the policy, but genetic tests are
excluded. Third
trimester test and delivery include
growth scans, non-stress tests,
and weekly consultations.
Both normal and C-section deliveries are covered
under the insurance, but cosmetic
treatments or special diets are not. Let's
understand IVF and natural
pregnancy coverage. IVF
treatments are also covered under the policy,
but you need to keep waiting periods in
mind. Generally, there is a waiting period of two to three
years if you are
opting for IVF treatment.
If you are conceiving naturally, the
policy also covers pregnancy-related expenses.
Now, let's understand maternity-
related expenses. If we do
n't have maternity coverage, these expenses can be very
high, which we may have to pay out of our own pocket.
If you live in tier-one cities
like Delhi, Mumbai, Bengaluru, or
Chennai, your expenses may be higher.  The cost
for a normal delivery can go from Rs 70,000 to Rs 5 lakh, whereas
if we talk about C-section, then this
expense can be above Rs 5 lakh. Talking about tier two
cities like Indore, Kochi,
Jaipur, then your expense can be Rs 00 to Rs 1 lakh
for a normal delivery and the cost of a C-section can
go above Rs 1 lakh. Talking about tier three
cities like Agra, Mysore,
Vijayawada, here your expense can be Rs 50,000 to Rs
70,000 for a normal delivery
and the cost of a C-section can go above Rs 70,000.
But apart from this, there are
also expenses for ultrasound tests, newborn baby coverage, which we call pre and
post natal. If you have a
good maternity health insurance plan, then
all your expenses will also be covered in it.
Therefore, it is very important that if you are
planning a family or are already
pregnant, then you consider a good maternity
plan so that you are
stress-free during that beautiful phase and your  There is
no financial burden on the above. If you are thinking
about getting a good maternity plan, you
can click on the link given in the description or you
can also call the number given on your screen. If
someone in your friends or family is
thinking about family planning,
then definitely share this video with them and
like this video and subscribe to our channel.